[{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the same vowel sound as the one represented by the letters underlined<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>B<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">oo<\/span>k<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Cool","Cook","Fool","Tool"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the same vowel sound as the one represented by the letters underlined<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Vill<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">a<\/span>ge<\/strong><\/p>","options":["page","pig","made","came"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the same vowel sound as the one represented by the letters underlined<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>P<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">a<\/span>tch<\/strong><\/p>","options":["starch","fare","mad","brave"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the same consonant sound as the one represented by the letter underlined<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong><span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">H<\/span>air<\/strong><\/p>","options":["heir","hour","honest","house"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the same consonant sound as the one represented by the letter underlined<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Edi<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">t<\/span>ion<\/strong><\/p>","options":["bash","catch","bastion","rating"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the appropraite stress pattern from the options. The syllables are written in capital letters<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Demarcation<\/strong><\/p>","options":["demarCAtion","deMARcation","DEmarcation","demarcaTION"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the appropraite stress pattern from the options. The syllables are written in capital letters<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>impossible<\/strong><\/p>","options":["imPOSsible","ImposSIble","IMpossible","impossiBLE"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the appropraite stress pattern from the options. The syllables are written in capital letters<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>imperialism<\/strong><\/p>","options":["imperiaLISM","imPErialism","impeRIAlism","IMperialism"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the stress on the first syllable<\/strong><\/p>","options":["madam","eighteen","invent","command"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the stress on the first syllable<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["nineteen","mother","estate","announce"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that has the stress on the first syllable<\/strong><\/p>","options":["commute","import(verb)","intend","export(noun)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The word in capital letters has the emphatic stress, choose the option to which the given sentence relates<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The traditional chief NARRATED the story to the children<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the children heard the story from the traditional chief","who narrated the story to the children?","the children could not listen to the story by the traditional chief","did the chief hide the story from the children?"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The word in capital letters has the emphatic stress, choose the option to which the given sentence relates<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The cat DEVOURED the rat<\/strong><\/p>","options":["did the rat devour the cat?","what devoured the rat?","did the cat pet the rat?","is this the rat that the cat devoured?"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>An autobiographical novel is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A novel written about another novelist","b.A true account of a novelist&#39s life by himself","A novel in which the novelist draws mainly on materials from his own life","A novel using the &#39I&#39 pronoun"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Plot in prose fiction is best defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The cause and \u0097 effect sequence of events","The brief summary of events",".The central event","The subject \u0097 matter of a novel"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is not true about unity of action in a novel?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Action may be unified through a single main character","Action may be unified by being set in one place","Action may be unified by many characters",".Action may be unified by having one consistent point of view"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Action in a novel is best defined as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The summary of the novel\u0092s story","What the characters do or say in the novel","The numerous sub \u0097 plots of the novel put together",".The totality of all the episodes in a novel leading to the conclusion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Suspense in a novel means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The postponement of the hero<span>'<\/span>s death till the last possible moment","The intense emotions that the author conveys","The inconclusive end of a novel","When we are curious about what happens next in a"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A realistic novel is one in which the characters are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Real","Historic","Just of above average intelligence","The types that we meet in everyday life"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Theme is best defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The subject matter of a novel or play","Central idea in a play or novel","The point of view in that novel",".The sum \u0097 total of all the characters experiences"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>What figure of speech does the following quotation<\/strong><br \/><strong>contain? Life&rsquo;s but a walking shadow (Macbeth)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A metaphor","An image","A synecdoche","An allusion"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statement is most true about<\/strong><br \/><strong>poetry?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The meaning of words are more important than their sounds","The sounds of words are more important than their meanings","The sound of words are often more important than their meanings","Sounds and meanings of words are of little consequence"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these best define exposition in drama?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The author<span>&#39;<\/span>s own general introduction to the play","The author<span>&#39;<\/span>s early exposure of his dramatist personae to conflict","Introduction to the characters and the general problem with which the play deals","The first performance of the play on stage"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the speaker in a poem cannot be identified with<\/strong><br \/><strong>the poet, that speaker is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A persona","A dramatist persona","A soliloquist","Aventriloquist"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these definitions best describes a lyric?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A short poem","A short poem in which the poet himself is speaking","A poem expressing a personal idea, feeling or mood","A poem divided into stanzas"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Among rocks, I am the loose one, among arrows, I am<\/strong><br \/><strong>the heart among daughters, I am the recluse, among<\/strong><br \/><strong>sons, the one who dies young <\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>What kind of repetition is used in the extract?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Anaphora","Single word repetition","Line repetition","Phrase repetition"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Apart from emphasis, what other effect does the<\/strong><br \/><strong>repetition have?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Makes the poem rhythmical","Makes the poem tedious","Makes the poem monotonous","Makes the poem exhilarating"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following line from poem Western wind, when will<\/strong><br \/><strong>thou blow? Is an example of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rhetorical question","Caesura","Alliteration","Nature imagery"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Identify the odd one out of these types of imagery<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Visual imagery","Tactile imagery","Synaesthesia","Literal imagery"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>When a poet uses mainly soft vowel sounds in a<\/strong><br \/><strong>poem, the texture of the poem is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mellifluous","Harsh","Assonantal","Neutral"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The sounds in the following lines may be described as<\/strong><br \/><strong>an example of: The moan of doves in immemorial elms,<\/strong><br \/><strong>and murmuring of innumerable bees<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Alliteration","Euphony","Cacophony","A mixture of all above"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The man dies in him who keeps silent in the face of<\/strong><br \/><strong>tyranny&rdquo;. This statement can be described as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Metaphoric","Literal","Tragic","A simile"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The literary technique in which a reader is taken to<\/strong><br \/><strong>the past of a current action is known as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rewinding","Fast forward","Flashback","Repetition"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that best completes the meaning of this sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The manager failed to control his staff because he was very ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rash","indiscreet","reckless","tactless"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that best completes the meaning of this sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The usefulness of the fertilizer in modern farming should be widely ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["diffused","disseminated","spread","scattered"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that best completes the meaning of this sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>He was the only candidate who failed the interview, so he had to bear his ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["disaster","misfortune","catastrophe","calamity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The officer has commended the&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">cordial<\/span> relationship existing between the soldiers and the civilians&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["disordered","confused","strained","unfortunate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Many foreign experts would like to establish in this country because the environment is&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">congenial<\/span><\/strong><\/p>","options":["hostile","inhospitable","aggressive","offensive"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The new chairman has exhibited&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">prudence<\/span> in his handling of the revenue<\/strong><\/p>","options":["impudence","shabbiness","dishonesty","recklessness"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>There is no point&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">dissipating<\/span> energy on a useless argument<\/strong><\/p>","options":["destroying","marshalling","storing","conserving"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>There is much&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">apathy<\/span> among youths nowadays towards reading novels<\/strong><\/p>","options":["indecision","indifference","enthusiasm","inclination"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is SIMILAR in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>We consider the recent silver jubilee celebration in the state a very&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">historic<\/span> event<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["important","memorable","ancient","critical"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is SIMILAR in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>One of the candidates was handed over to the police for attending the interview with&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">spurious<\/span> credentials<\/strong><\/p>","options":["false","incomplete","unsigned","altered"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is SIMILAR in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>There is a theory that&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">postulates<\/span> that all Nigerian languages derive from one source<\/strong><\/p>","options":["confirms","affirms","suggests","emphasizes"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that is SIMILAR in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The candidate was disqualified as a result of his <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">irreverent<\/span> behaviour<\/strong><\/p>","options":["shameful","disrespectful","careless","abnormal"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that best completes the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The rain ... when the accident took place<\/strong><\/p>","options":["has stopped","stopped","was stopped","had stopped"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that best completes the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Players for next FIFA world competition have been ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["choosen","chosed","chosen","choosed"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that best completes the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The boy was ... by snake early this morning<\/strong><\/p>","options":["beaten","bitten","bit","bite"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option that best completes the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>It is desirable that you ... there when wehe arrives<\/strong><\/p>","options":["be","are","will be","should be"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The teacher warned her students against resting on their laurels<\/strong><\/p>","options":["relaxing on soft chairs","taking things for granted","depending on past achievements","feeling satisfied and making no new effort"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that best completes the meaning in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The door handle was shaky because the screws had ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lost","loosed","losed","loosened"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that best completes the meaning in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The lawyer pleaded with the Judge to ... justice with mercy<\/strong><\/p>","options":["tempar","temper","tamper","taper"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the word that best completes the meaning in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Obi bought five novels last week and have gone through all. He is totally a ... reader<\/strong><\/p>","options":["vicarious","voracious","vivacious","veracious"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option NEAREST in meaning to the word in italics<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>He lost his voice&nbsp;<em>momentarily<\/em><\/strong><\/p>","options":["in a moment","in a split moment","for a brief period of time","without delay"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option NEAREST in meaning to the word in italics<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>In some parts of India, people are&nbsp;<em>ostracized&nbsp;<\/em>simply because of their ancestry<\/strong><\/p>","options":["abandoned","shut off from society","refused education","rendered unhappy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the words or phrase which best fills the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>... him in the crowd, I would have told you at once<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["Had it been I saw","If I saw","Had I seen","Should I see"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the words(s) or phrase which best fills the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>... he had insufficient qualification, he was denied admission&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hence","For the fact","Being that","As"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>We watched the woman as she stood up and _______ herself more comfortably<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reseated","Resat","Reseat","Resitted"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Chidi is naturally taciturn<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Friendly","Cheerful","Dumb","Seriously"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Whenever he put the lighten, someone_____ to disturb him.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Came","Comes","Has come","Would come"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Whenever he put the lighten, someone ______ to disturb him.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Came","Comes","Has come","Would come"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Some smugglers have created a road diversion in order to ... the new import duty laws<\/strong><\/p>","options":["circurrflex","circumscibe","circumspect","circumvent"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>It happened that our dog is a male but ... are all females<\/strong><\/p>","options":["theirs"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>He travels very often as if he does not know that a car runs ... petrol<\/strong><\/p>","options":["with","by","on","in"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>We were all delighted when the lady ... a bouncing baby boy<\/strong><\/p>","options":["delivered","brought forth","gave bath to","was delivered of"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>You are driving too fast for safety<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the speed is alright and safe","the speed is not fast enough for safety","the speed is not entirely safe","you should drive faster to ensure safety"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>For all I care, the man may be dead<\/strong><\/p>","options":["I am not sure the man is dead","I am not interested in his death","I very much care in case he is dead"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the most appropraite option OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The priest was invited to&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">consecrate<\/span> the new building<\/strong><\/p>","options":["destroy","tarnish","abuse","pollute"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the most appropraite option OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>A majority of those who sat for the last JAMB examination are&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">sanguine<\/span> of success<\/strong><\/p>","options":["hopeful","pessimistic","unsure","disheartened"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the most appropraite option OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>When we woke up this morning the sky was&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">overcast<\/span><\/strong><\/p>","options":["cloudy","clear","shiny","brilliant"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the most appropraite option OPPOSITE in meaning to the underlined word<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Enemies of progress&nbsp;<span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">covertly<\/span> strive to undermine efforts of this administration<\/strong><\/p>","options":["secretely","boldly","consistently","overtly"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The boy is constantly under some... that he is the best student in the class<\/strong><\/p>","options":["elusion","illusion","delusion","allusion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Her parents did not approve of the marriage two years ago because she had not reach her ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["maturity","majority","puberty","minority"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Our teacher ... the importance of reading over our work before submission<\/strong><\/p>","options":["emphasized on","flayed emphasis on","emphasized","put emphasis"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Young men should not get mixed ... politics<\/strong><\/p>","options":["in with","up with","up in","on with"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option NEAREST in meaning to the word or phrase in italics<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Much to his&nbsp;<em>chagrin&nbsp;<\/em>did not win the race<\/strong><\/p>","options":["stupefaction","disappointment","shock","surprise"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option NEAREST in meaning to the word in italics<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Traditional rulers are not supposed to be involved in&nbsp;<em>partisan&nbsp;<\/em>politics&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["dirty","party","modem","part-time"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choose the option NEAREST in meaning to the word in italics<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Mr. Adamu is a&nbsp;<em>dominant<\/em> partner in our business<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["a prominent","an important","an outstanding","an influential"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The Lawyer pleaded with the Judge to ... justice with mercy<\/strong><\/p>","options":["tern par","temper","tamper","taper"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>So far, no... drug has been discovered as a cure for the AIDS disease<\/strong><\/p>","options":["effected","efficient","efficacious","effectual"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fill the gap with the most appropriate option from the list following the gap<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The student leader were ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["unduly","undully","unduely","unduelly"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The words in capital letters have the emphatic stress. Choose the option that best fit the expression in the sentence<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>The secretary enjoys travelling AT NIGHT<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Did the secretary enjoy travelling by day?","Does the secretary enjoy travelling by day?","Who enjoys travelling at night?","Does the secretary hate travelling at night?"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"}]